Guide to the Xavier University Board of Trustees meeting minutes and related materials
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Board of Trustees meeting minutes and related materials
1840-2009
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Board of Trustees
16.8 linear feet (48 boxes)
Xavier University Board of Trustees meeting materials and related documents. Meeting dates begin with 1840 and conclude with 5/8/2009.
XUA- 14
History of Xavier University Board of Trustees
The Xavier University Board of Trustees is the primary governance body at the university. As such, it has a broad array of responsibilities over policy making and implementation. The Xavier Board of Trustees was first established in 1840 with the institution of St. Xavier College. Until the appointment of lay persons to the Board in July, 1972, the Board of Trustees had been solely composed of members of the Society of Jesus.
Membership, authority, responsibilities of the Xavier Board of Trustees has evolved over the years. The Xavier University Board of Trustees' Code of Regulations (2011 revision) gives the following information: Article II: Membership of Board of Trustees: A. The Board of Trustees shall consist of that number of Trustees as shall be determined from time to time by the Board of Trustees, but which number shall not be less than 15 nor more than 50 persons, excluding Trustees Emeriti. At no time shall the number of Trustees who are also members of the Society of Jesus be less than 15% of the total number of Trustees. The President of Xavier University and the Rector of the Jesuit Community shall be an ex officio voting member of the Board of Trustees, and both shall be included among the number of Jesuit Trustees in determining if the minimum number of Jesuit Trustees is satisfied. The National Chair-University Trustee of the National Alumni Association shall also be an ex officio voting member of the Board of Trustees, and shall serve for a three-year term commencing with the meeting of the Board of Trustees following appointment as National Chair-University Trustee of the National Alumni Association. B. The Trustees shall be divided into three classes, each class consisting of one-third (as nearly as possible) of the total number of Trustees. Trustees shall ordinarily serve for three-year terms and be eligible for reelection to a maximum of 2 full consecutive terms. A person shall not be eligible for election to serve an additional term, unless such person is nominated by the Executive Committee and elected by an affirmative vote of 2/3 of the Trustees. The Trustees who serve as officers shall be exempt from this provision until at least 1 year has passed following completion of their term of office... Article III: Board Authority and Responsibilities: A. The Board of Trustees shall have the authority to exercise all powers of an Ohio non-profit corporation prescribed by law. The Trustees shall have general responsibility and authority for planning, executing and evaluating all general, academic and financial policies governing the operation of the University and shall be responsible for the University's financial health and welfare. The Board of Trustees shall exercise ultimate institutional authority as set forth in this Code of Regulations and in such other policy documents it deems to be appropriate. This Code of Regulations and other Board policy statements shall take precedence over all other institutional statements, documents and policies. B. The Board of Trustees shall have the authority to carry out all lawful functions that are permitted by this Code of Regulations or by the Articles of Incorporation. This authority, in consultation with the President, shall include but not be limited to these illustrative functions: 1. Determine and periodically review the University's mission and purposes. 2. Promote and maintain the commitment of the University to the Jesuit tradition. 3. Elect the President of the University, who shall be a member of the Society of Jesus, who shall be the executive and administrative head of the University in all its activities and divisions, and set appropriate terms of employment, including compensation. 4. Annually assess the President's performance based on mutually agreed-upon goals and other criteria. 5. Review and consider for approval proposed material changes in the University's academic programs and other major enterprises consistent with the University's mission, plans and financial resources. 6. Approve institutional policies bearing on faculty appointment, promotion, tenure and dismissal as well as personnel or antidiscrimination policies for other categories of employees. 7. Approve the annual budget and tuition and fees, regularly monitor the University's financial condition, and establish policy guidelines affecting all institutional assets, including investment in the physical plant. 8. Contribute financially to the University fund-raising goals, participate actively in strategies to secure sources of support, and authorize University officers to accept gifts or bequests subject to Board policy guidelines. 9. Authorize any debt financing and approve the securitization of loans. 10. Authorize the construction of new buildings and major renovations of existing buildings. 11. Authorize the purchase, sale and management of lands, buildings or major equipment. 12. Approve all earned and honorary degrees through the faculty and President, as they shall recommend. 13. Periodically undertake assessment of the Board's performance....Article VI: Meeting of the Trustees: A. The Board of Trustees shall have 4 regular meetings annually on such dates and at such places as it shall determine....Article VIII: Committees: A. The Board shall establish an Executive Committee...a Jesuit Identity Committee, a Finance Committee, and Audit Committee and such other standing and ad-hoc committees as it deems appropriate to the discharge of its responsibilities..." (Source: Xavier University Board of Trustees' Code of Regulations (Revised 12/2/2011)
Scope and Content
Meeting minutes and related content from the Xavier University Board of Trustees.
Statement of Arrangement
In Series I is the primary, official set of meeting minutes which are arranged chronologically within either calendar year (from 1840 to 1962) or academic year (from 1963/1964 to the present). In a separate Series II supplementary materials are arranged by chronology.
Separated Material
A micofilm copy of the Xavier University Board of Trustees meeting minutes are separately housed in the Xavier University Archives.
Restrictions on Access
Restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.
Other Finding Aid
Housed with the collection are more detailed contents notes for these materials. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.
Accruals
There may be additional materials added to this collection at a later date.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Administration
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Series I: Primary Set, Meeting Minutes, 1840-2009
  - Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1840-1931 (Box 1)
  - Xavier Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1932-1945 (Box 2)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1946-1955 (Box 3)
  - Xavier University Bard of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1956-1962 (Box 4)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1967-1969 (Box 7)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 9)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1971-1973 (Box 10)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 11)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 12)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1980-1983 (Box 13)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1983-1985 (Box 14)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1985-1987 (Box 15)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 16)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1989-1991 (Box 17)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1991-1993 (Box 18)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1993-1994 (Box 19)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1994-1995 (Box 20)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1995-1996 (Box 21)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 22)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 23)
    - 1997-1998 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1997 September 26 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1997 December 12 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1998 February 27 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1998 May 8 (Folder 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1998-1999 (Box 24)
    - 1998-1999 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1998 September 25 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1998 December 4 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1999 February 26 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1999 May 7 (Folder 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1999-2000 (Box 25)
    - 1999-2000 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1999 September 24 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1999 December 3 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2000 February 18 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2000 May 12 (Folder 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2000-2001 (Box 26)
    - 2000-2001 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2000 September 22 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2000 December 1 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2001 February 23 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2001 May 18 (Folder 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2001-2002 (Box 27)
    - 2001-2002 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2001 September 28 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2001 December 7 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2002 February 22 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2002 May 17 (Folder 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2002-2003 (Box 28)
    - 2002-2003 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2002 September 27 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2002 December 6 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2003 February 21 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2003 May 2 (Folder 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2003-2004 (Box 29)
    - 2003-2004 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2003 September 26 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2003 December 5 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2004 February 20 (Folder 4)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2003-2004 (Box 30)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2004 May 7 (Folder 1)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2004-2005 (Box 31)
    - 2004-2005 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2004 September 24 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2004 December 3 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2005 February 18 (Folder 4)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2004-2005 (Box 32)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2005 May 6 (Folder 1)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2005-2006 (Box 33)
    - 2005-2006 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2005 September 30 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2005 December 2 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2006 February 17 (Folder 4)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2005-2006 (Box 34)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2006 May 12 (Folder 1)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2006-2007 (Box 35)
    - 2006-2007 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2006 September 29 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2006 December 1 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2007 February 16 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2007 May 11 (Folder 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2007-2008 (Box 36)
    - 2007-2008 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2007 September 28 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2007 December 7 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2008 February 29 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2008 May 9 (Folder 5)
  - Xavier University Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2008-2009 (Box 37)
    - 2008-2009 Academic Year General Information (Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2008 September 26 (Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2008 December 12 (Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2009 February 27 (Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2009 May 8 (Folder 5)
- Series II: Supplementary Materials, 1842-1994; 1957-1994
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1842-1970, bulk 1957-1970 (Box 1)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1842-1948 (Folder 1A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1957-1959 (Folder 1B)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1961-1962 (Folder 2)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1963-1964 (Folder 3)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1964-1965 (Folder 4)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1965-1966 (Folder 5)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1966-1967 (Folder 6)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1967-1968 (Folder 7)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1968-1969 (Folder 8)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1969 April-August (Folder 9)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1969-1970 (Folder 10)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1970 April-August (Folder 11)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1970 September-December (Folder 12)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1971 January-March (Folder 13)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1971 April-August (Folder 14)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1971 September 11 (Folder 15)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1971 December 12 (Folder 16)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1972 January 6 (Folder 17)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1972 February 12 (Folder 18)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1972 April 6 (Folder 19)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1972 June 14 (Folder 20A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1972-1974 (Folder 20B)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1972 September 29 (Folder 21)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1973 January 5 (Folder 22)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1973 April 13 (Folder 23)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1973 June 1 (Folder 24)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1973 September 26 (Folder 25)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1973 December 19 (Folder 26)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1974 March 27 (Folder 27)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1974 May 29 (Folder 28)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1974-1979 (Box 4)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1974 September 25 (Folder 29)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1974 December 19 (Folder 30)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1975 March 19 (Folder 31)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1975 May 28 (Folder 32)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1975 October 1 (Folder 33)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1975 December 17 (Folder 34)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1976 March 24 (Folder 35)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1976 May 26 (Folder 36)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1976 September 29 (Folder 37)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1976 December 15 (Folder 38)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1977 March 23 (Folder 39)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1977 May 25 (Folder 40)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1977 September 21 (Folder 41)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1977 December 14 (Folder 42)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1978 March 21 (Folder 43)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1978 May 24 (Folder 44)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1978 September 27 (Folder 45)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1978 December 13 (Folder 46)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1979 March 14 (Folder 47)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1979-1986 (Box 5)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1979 May 9 (Folder 48)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1979 September-December (Folder 49)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1980 March-May (Folder 50)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1980-1981 (Folder 51)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1981-1982 (Folder 52)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1982-1983 (Folder 53)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1983 October-December (Folder 54)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1984 March-May (Folder 55A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1984-1985 (Folder 55B)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1984 October-December (Folder 56)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1985 March-May (Folder 57)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1985 July-October (Folder 58A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1985-1986 (Folder 58B)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1985-1988 (Box 6)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1985 December 4 (Folder 59)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1986 February 24 (Folder 60)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1986 May 1 (Folder 61A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1986-1987 (Folder 61B)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1986 October 8 (Folder 62)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1986 December 3 (Folder 63)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1987 March 4 (Folder 64)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1987 May 13 (Folder 65A)
    - Supplementary Materials Executive Committee Minutes, 1987-1988 (Folder 65B)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1987-1989 (Box 7)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1987 September 30 (Folder 66)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1987 September 30 (Folder 67)
    - Supplementary Materials Trustees Leadership Retreat, 1987 October (Folder 67A)
    - Supplementary Materials Trustee Leadership Retreat, 1987 October (Folder 67B)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1987 December 9 (Folder 68)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1988 March 2 (Folder 69)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1988 May 17 (Folder 70)
    - Supplementary Materials 1988-1989 Minutes of the Board's Executive Committee (Folder 70A)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1988 September 28 (Folder 71)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1988 September 28 (Folder 72)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1988 December 7 (Folder 73)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1988 December 7 (Folder 74)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1989 March-May (Folder 75)
    - Supplementary Materials 1989-1990 Minutes of the Board's Executive Committee (Folder 75A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1989 September 29 (Folder 76)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1989 September 29 (Folder 77)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1989 December 8 (Folder 78)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1989 December 8 (Folder 79)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1990 March 9 (Folder 80)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1990 March 9 (Folder 81)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1990 May 11 (Folder 82)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1990 September 10 (Folder 82A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1990 September 28 (Folder 83)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1990 September 28 (Folder 84)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1990 November 27 (Folder 84A)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1990-1991 (Box 10)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1990 December 7 (Folder 85)
    - Supplementary Materials Minutes of the Board's Executive Committee, 1991 February 26 (Folder 85A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1991 March 8 (Folder 86)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1991 May 10 (Folder 87)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1991 September 27 (Folder 88)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1991 December 6 (Folder 89)
    - Supplementary Materials President J. Hoff's Notes, 1991 December 6 (Folder 90)
    - Supplementary Materials Vice President John F. Kucia's Notes, 1991 December 6 (Folder 91)
  - Board of Trustees Supplementary Materials, 1992-1994 (Box 11)
    - Supplementary Materials Minutes of the Board's Executive Committee, 1992 February (Folder 91A)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1992 March 6 (Folder 92)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1992 March 6 (Folder 93)
    - Supplementary Materials Vice President's Joan Connell's Notes, 1992 March 6 (Folder 94)
    - Supplementary Materials Vice President John F. Kucia's Notes, 1992 March 6 (Folder 95)
    - Supplementary Materials, 1992 May 8 (Folder 96)
    - Supplementary Materials Notes of Acting Academic Vice President William J. Larkin III, 1992-1993 (Folder 97)
    - Supplementary Materials Notes of Academic Vice President James E. Bundschuh, 1993-1994 (Folder 98)